"Can Vitamin E or Selenium Supplements
Prevent or Treat Alzheimer's?"
Oxidative stress
from free radicals
is the one of the pathways
implicated in the development
and deterioration
of Alzheimer's brains,
given the evidence of excess
oxidative DNA damage on autopsy.
So, what about trying
an antioxidant?
Vitamin E levels
tend to be lower
in the bloodstreams of those
with cognitive impairment
or dementia,
but which came first?
Maybe Alzheimer's disease
led to poor eating,
rather than poor eating
leading to Alzheimer's disease.
Greater vitamin E intake
from foods
is clearly associated
with a lower risk
of developing Alzheimer's,
but greater vitamin E intake
from supplements is not.
But, that didn't stop
researchers
from including a vitamin E arm
in the largest primary
prevention study
of Alzheimer's disease to date.
The Prevention
of Alzheimer's Disease
by Vitamin E and Selenium trial
randomized more than
7500 older men
to take vitamin E, selenium,
both, or neither-just placebos-
for five years.
To quote from the conclusion:
"Neither supplement
prevented dementia."
A separate long-term vitamin E
supplementation trial
of older women similarly found
no protection
against cognitive decline.
Neither did vitamin E
appear to benefit those
with mild cognitive impairment,
but the trials on Alzheimer's
patients themselves
started to get more interesting.
The first trial,
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine,
randomized more than 150
Alzheimer's patients
to vitamin E or placebo
to see if vitamin E could slow
the progression of the disease.
The primary outcome
was the number of days
until of one of any
of the following happened:
death, institutionalization,
loss of the ability
to perform basic activities
of daily living,
or sliding into severe dementia,
where you suffer
a complete loss
of sense of time or place.
On first analysis,
vitamin E flopped:
no significant slowing
of progression.
Digging deeper,
the researchers realized
that despite
the random allotment,
the placebo group
just by chance
ended up with patients
with milder disease.
After taking that into account,
the difference in outcomes
between the vitamin E
and placebo groups
widened substantially.
Now, this kind of
unplanned post-hoc analysis
is heavily frowned upon,
but the effect
seemed so sizable
they went ahead
and published it.
In the placebo group,
the adjusted time to death
or loss of independence
was 440 days,
but in the vitamin E group,
after the baseline cognition
was normalized,
it was 670 days,
more than seven months later.
However,
given the unorthodox analysis,
the scientific world waited
for the study to be replicated.
And here we go:
more than 600 patients
with mild to moderate
Alzheimer's disease
were subsequently randomized
to vitamin E supplements,
the drug memantine, both,
or neither (just placebos)
for two years.
Although there was no slowing
of cognitive decline
after adjusting
for multiple comparisons,
there was a slowing
of functional decline,
in terms of managing
daily activities
like bathing or dressing.
The vitamin E group
appeared to only suffer
about 1.5 years
of functional deterioration
in the two years' time,
resulting in approximately
two hours less caregiver time
required each day
compared to the drug group.
If those were the only two
clinical vitamin E trials,
I would give vitamin E
serious consideration
for those
with Alzheimer's disease.
But, there's a third,
a six-month trial,
that suggested vitamin E
may be detrimental
to cognition
in some Alzheimer's patients.
Obviously, more research
needs to be done.
In my next video,
I'll cover other antioxidants
that have been put to the test,
including vitamin C,
beta carotene,
Centrum multivitamin,
and the minerals
zinc and calcium.